Guide to the Julia Ruuttila Papers 1878-2004
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
- Activism and Organizations, circa 1920-1988; Series B
  - Federated Auxiliaries
    - Oregon state, circa 1920; 1929
      - Legislature--directory of committee rooms, 35th Legislative Assembly, 1929 (Box-folder 2/25)
    - Oregon State Federation of Labor (AFL)--leaflet, "An Exposé of the Anti-Labor Bill" (Ballot Measure 317), 1938 (Box-folder 2/26)
    - People's World--flier, testimonial to Floyd Ramp, Portland, Oregon, 1975 January 26 (Box-folder 2/27)
    - Petition re. Medicare and Social Security, 1980 (Box-folder 2/28)
      Signed by residents of Marshall Union Manor, addressed to Mark Hatafield, Bob Packwood, and Les AuCoin.
    - Poor Peoples Alliance (Portland, Oregon)--bus petition asking lower fares, undated (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Portland Labor Unity Council--flier, circa 1940 (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Radical Education Project (Detroit, Michigan)--pamphlet, Double Jeopardy: to be Black and Female, circa 1970 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - St. Johns workers (Portland, Oregon)--resolution condemning relief agencies, 1937 November 12 (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Unions--list of locals in Oregon, by location, undated (Box-folder 2/33)
    - United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners Ladies Auxiliary--ritual, 1927 (Box-folder 2/34)
    - United States Senate--report, "Violation of Free Speech and Rights of Labor", 1937 (Box-folder 2/35)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom--circular letter asking support of Bail Fund, 1972 (Box-folder 2/36)
- Manuscripts, circa 1935-1991; Series C
  Selected typescript manuscripts by Julia Ruuttila include a never-published novel, The Wolf at the Door, as well as articles, biographical sketches, memorials and obituaries, poetry, speeches, and testimony at hearings. The folders are arranged alphabetically by type of materials, and chronologically thereunder. Folder descriptions list names she wrote under.
  - Articles
    - By Kathleen Cronin, 1953; 1959
      - "The Sage of Yoncalla" [about Jesse Applegate by Kathleen Cronin], 1953 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - "The Great-Hearted Strangers" [published as "Forgotten men in Oregon's History," People's World, 1959 June 13] (Box-folder 3/1)
      - "What the Foreign Man Said to Dan McGann" [published as "Economic base: native timber, foreign labor," People's World, 1959 June 20] (Box-folder 3/1)
      - "The Union Card in the Red Plaid Pocket" [Labor's great awakening in Oregon," People's World, 19519 June 27] (Box-folder 3/1)
    - By Julia Ruuttila, circa 1970-1979
      - "Origin and Meaning of the Peace Symbol", circa 1970 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - "Viet Nam" [sic], circa 1970 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Untitled [re. Cheryl James case], 1972 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - "The 1948 Strike, Portland", circa 1975 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Untitled [re. federal legislation to ban log exports], 1978 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Untitled [report of Bloody July 5 memorial speech by Everett Ede], 1978 [?] (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Untitled [report of Pacific Northwest Labor History Association 60th anniversary commemoration of Centralia tragedy], 1979 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - By Julia Ruuttila, 1980; circa 1980
      - Untitled [memories of the waterfront strike, 1934], 1980 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - "Cowtown in the Eagle Valley", circa 1980 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Untitled [Joe Hill, one-time Longview, Washington, longshoreman, and his book of poetry, We Are Portland Too!], circa 1980 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Untitled [Astoria and Finnish immigrants], circa 1980] (Box-folder 3/3)
      - "ILWU" [re. Bloody July 5 commemoration and Francis J. Murnane], circa 1980 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Autobiography [fragments], "Only the Lonely", 1970 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Biographical sketches, tributes by others, and maternal genealogy, 1972-1991 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Book--untitled, re. civil rights [partial], circa 1975 (Box-folder 3/6)
      Chapter titles include: "The Civil Rights Law," "The Fair Employment Practices Act: Discrimination by the Employers and Jimcrow [sic] in the Unions," "Discrimination in the Civil Service," "Legal Redress," "The Negro in Politics," "The Vanport Flood," "Jimcrow [sic] in Death," "No Room at the Inn," "Does Education Draw a Color Line in Portland?" "The NAACP," "Role of the Urban League," and "Housing: Last Beachhead of Bigotry."
    - Interview--Blake Harris (Vancouver, British Columbia), undated (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Memoir-- The Bridges of Cé [foreword, chapter titles, and conclusion only], circa 1960 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Memorials and obituaries, 1962-1982 (Box-folder 3/9)
      Subjects: Oscar Ruuttila, Delbert Dietz, John Zeide, and Harold Pritchett [memorial folder].
    - Notes, undated (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Novel--The Wolf at the Door, circa 1938 (Box-folder 3/11-17)
    - Poetry, circa 1935-circa 1985 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Poetry--Rhea's Garden of Verses, 1971 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Speeches, class presentations, etc., 1937-1987; undated
      - Untitled, re. need for relief assistance for wood workers, public meeting, [1937] (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - "How Labor Goals Have Changed During the Growth of the Trade Union Movement," Astoria High School, circa 1964 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - "Bonafides," unidentified school, circa 1970 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, re. Angela Davis, 1971 January (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, re. Labor History, Roosevelt High School, Portland, Oregon, 1971 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, Julia's 65th birthday celebration, 1972 April (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, re. political prisoners, Unitarian Church, Vancouver, Washington, 1972 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - "Westward the Course of Empire Holds Its Sway," social studies class, unidentified school, 1974 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - "Women in the Labor Movement: A Personal Overview," Pacific Northwest Labor History Conference, 1975 May 9 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, re. politcs, political science class, Oregon State University, Corvallis, 1975 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, re. Spanish Civil War, Roosevelt High School, Portland, Oregon, 1978 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, thank you speech for ILWU award, presented in San Francisco, 1978 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Untitled, re. anti-war movement and ILWU, 1978 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - "Why Unions? The Labor Movement in the Northwest", [one version may have been for radio broadcast, circa 1985 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
      - Comments on the book, Blue Collar Marriage by Mirra Komarovsky, conference presentation, 1987 (Box-folder 4/1-4)
    - Testimony at hearings, 1966; 1975; 1977; 1980
      - In protest of police violence, Portland City Council, 1966 (Box-folder 4/5)
      - In opposition to a Pacific Power and Light rate increase, 1975 (Box-folder 4/5)
      - On behalf of ILWU Women's Auxiliary No. 5 in support of the Health Security Act, 1977 October 7 (Box-folder 4/5)
      - In support of Kennedy-Waxman bills on health care, 1980 (Box-folder 4/5)
- Published Materials and Writings by Others, 1925-1990; Series D
  The series is organized into two subseries: 1) Published Materials and 2) Writings by Others.
  - Published Materials, 1925-1990; Sub-series 1
    The published writings of Julia Ruuttila are arranged by type of publication: magazine, newsletter, and newspaper, and thereunder chronologically. The names she wrote under are listed in the content description. Following those files are newspapers clippings about Ruuttila and clippings she collected about subjects of interest, arranged chronologically.
    - Magazines, 1925-1974
      - "Shelling Peas" [poem by Julia Godman], Extension Monitor, 1925 (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "Welcome to America" [letter to the editor by Kathleen Cronin], The Nation, 1947 December 27 (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "The Caulk Boots are Marching: CIO Woodworkers United Behind a Fighting Program" [article by Kathleen Cronin, Northwest correspondent], March of Labor, 1952 March (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "What's Behind the Screen?" [first in series re. Coast Guard waterfront screening by R.J. Keenan, ghostwritten by Julia Ruuttila], March of Labor, 1952 April (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "Design for Union Busting" [second in series re. Coast Guard waterfront screening by R.J. Keenan, ghostwritten by Julia Ruuttila], March of Labor, 1952 May (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "United in the Sawdust Belt" [article by Kathleen Cronin], March of Labor, 1954 September (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "America's Stepchildren" [article by Julia Ruuttila], People's World Magazine, 1956 February 17 (Box-folder 4/6)
      - "The Life and Death of An American Town" [article by Kathleen Cronin], 1958 August (Box-folder 4/6)
    - "Christ May Have Begun It: Some comments on the struggle of the Have-nots against the Establishment" [article by Julia Ruuttila], Metropolis (Portland State University), 1974 (Box-folder Oversize folder 1)
    - Newsletter--ManorGram [Marshall Union Manor, Julia Ruuttila, editor), 1978 October-1985 October (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Newspapers, 1937-1990; undated
      - Letters to the editor of the Oregon Journal, 1937; 1951 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Articles in the Timber Worker by Julia G. Bertram, circa 1938-1940 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Articles in People's World and People's Daily World by Kathleen Cronin (including a series, "Oregon's First 100 Years" for the state centennial, 1959), 1945-1946 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Article in The Dispatcher by Kathleen Cronin, 1948 April 2 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Articles in The Changing Woman by Kathleen Ruuttila, 1972 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Poem, "Hello to the Night Star," by Julia Ruuttila, in the Oregonian, 1973 June 17 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Letter to the editor by Julia Ruuttila, Willamette Week, 1987 April 2 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Letter to the editor by Julia Ruuttila, Anchorage Daily News, 1990 August 18 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Poem, "The Heart's Geography," in an unidentified Finnish newspaper, possibly at Astoria, in memory of Oscar Ruuttila by Julia Ruuttila, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Articles by Kathleen Cronin in Daily Peoples World, 1947; 1958 (Box-folder Oversize folder 1)
    - Newspaper articles about Julia Ruuttila, 1948-1990 (Box-folder 4/9)
      Includes coverage of the firing from the Oregon Welfare Commission of Julia Eaton [Ruuttila], 1948, and Ruuttila's appearance at the House Un-American Activities Committee hearings in Seattle, 1956 December.
    - Newspaper articles collected by Julia Ruuttila, 1929-1966 (Box-folder 4/10)
      Topics include shipping, unions, strikes, log export ban, and Francis J. Murnane, labor leader.
    - Includes advertisement from Ralph and Stanley, Portland grocers, with anti-union message, 1938 February (Box-folder Oversize folder 2)
  - Writings by Others, 1950-1974; Sub-series 2
    Includes articles, a manuscript, a school report and speech arranged alphabetically by last names of the authors.
    "Elmer Smith, 'Wobbly Lawyer'," article, Industrial Worker, 1973 February
    Lumberjacks' Lawyer: The Story of Elmer Smith and the Centralia Tragedy of 1919, manuscript (rough draft), undated
    - Tom Copeland, 1973; undated (Box-folder 4/11)
    - John Godman, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 4/12)
      Articles by Julia Ruuttila's brother on hypnosis, The Huntsville Times (Alabama)
    - Irvin Goodman and John Caughlan, 1950 (Box-folder 4/13)
      "Laura Law--Murdered Labor Leader," manuscript chapter that appears as Chapter 2 of They Were Called Reds in Mss 1811, Irvin Goodman Papers.
    - "The Truth in the Case of Laura Law, Murdered Labor Leader"--tabloid version of chapter in 4/13, published by Civil Rights Congress, 1950 October (Box-folder Oversize folder 2)
    - John M. McClelland, Jr.--article, "Terror on Tower Avenue," Pacific Northwest Quarterly, 1966 April (Box-folder 4/14)
    - Michael Jack McDonald--poems by Julia Ruuttila's son, 1945; undated (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Harold Symonds--student report on socialism in Astoria, Oregon, 1965 (Box-folder 4/16)
      Cites a personal interview with Julia Ruuttila. Folder includes a letter Symmonds received from the United States Immigration and Naturalization Service in response to his request for information about deported Finnish aliens.
    - Speech by unidentified Filippino-American union leader at event honoring Martina G. Curl, undated (Box-folder 4/17)
- Research for Biography of Louise Bryant, 1878-1987; Series E
  The author, Virginia Gardner, received a Rabinowitz Foundation grant for reseach into Louise Bryant's background and youth. She arranged for Julia Ruuttila to conduct interviews and do other research for the Oregon portion of this work, beginning in 1970. In the course of this research, Gardner and Ruuttila corresponded, and Gardner sent Julia copies of correspondence from others on background. The book, Friend and Lover: The Life of Louise Bryant, was published in 1982. The series is organized into three subseries: 1) Virginia Gardner, 2) Julia Ruuttila, and 3) California and Nevada Research. It includes correspondence, interview notes and transcripts, manuscript, research materials (dates given are dates of materials, not dates they were collected), and book reviews.
  - Virginia Gardner, 1916-1987; Sub-series 1
    Virginia Gardner also signed herself Virginia Gardner Marberry and Virginia Marberry.
    - Outgoing Correspondence, 1970-1977; 1987 (Box-folder 5/1)
      Correspondents include: Bishop H. Jesse (Trinity Episcopal Church, Reno, Nevada), Julia Ruuttila (also addressed as Kathleen), Arthur Spencer (Oregon Historical Society, Portland), Charles Ashleigh (Sussex, England), Edmund Wilson (New York), Margaret Bome (Reno, Nevada), National Archives (Washington, D.C.), Kenneth Durant (East Jamaica, Vermont), Giovanni Gullace (Binghamton, New York), Diane McInychuk (Syracuse, New York), Hazel Hunkins-Hallinen, Horace V. Gregory (Palisades, New York), Anne Bullitt (Louise Bryant's daughter), Doris Alexander, and Robert A. Rosenstone.
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 5/2)
      Correspondents include: Charles A. Pierce (Tarrytown, New York), Sara Bard Field Wood (Berkeley, California), Miriam Van Waters (Framingham, Massachusetts), Hazel Hunkins-Hallinan, Doris Alexander, Robert A. Rosenstone, Louis Shaeffer, and Malcolm Cowley (Sherman, Connecticut).
    - Interviews, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5/3)
      Interviewees include: Andrew Dasburg (artist, Taos, New Mexico), Frank Touchet (psychologist), Kitty Cannell, and Albert Boni (New York).
    - Interviews--"Life Among the Bohemians: An Interview with Floyd Dell", 1968 October 31 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Notes, 1973 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Manuscript [partial draft] with outline, circa 1970 (Box-folder 5/6-12)
    - Research materials collected [photocopies], 1919-1934
      - Letters, Louise Bryant to Jack Reed, 1919 (Box-folder 5/13)
      - Letter, Sara Bard Field to Louise Bryant, 1922 January 26 (Box-folder 5/13)
      - Henry G. Reed letters to Robert Hallowell and Granville Hicks, 1934 October 6 (Box-folder 5/13)
    - Report of Louise Bryant's testimony before the Overman subcommittee of the United States Senate Judiciary Committee, 1919 February (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Louise Bryant's writing, 1916-1925; undated
      - "Two Judges" [typescript transcript], The Masses, 1916 April (Box-folder 5/15)
      - "The Poets' Revolution" [photocopy], The Masses, 1916 July (Box-folder 5/15)
      - Poem, "Aftermath" [typescript transcript], Current Opinion, 1922 July (Box-folder 5/15)
      - "A Turkish Divorce" [photocopy], The Nation, 1925 August 26 (Box-folder 5/15)
      - Poem, "Russian Memories" [typescript transcript], The Dial, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
      - Untitled manuscript re. Jack Reed [photocopy], undated (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Julia Ruuttila, 1878-1987; Sub-series 2
    Includes correspondence, typescript reports and transcripts of interviews, and photocopies of research materials. The correspondence not only reports results to Virginia Gardner, seeks information, and describes the research work, but also includes aspects of Ruuttila's life other than the Louise Bryant research project. Letters to Gardner are sometimes signed "Julia" and sometimes "Kathleen." The subseries also includes Julia's reviews of the completed book.
    - Outgoing Correspondence, 1970-1977; undated (Box-folder 5/16)
      Correspondents include: Virginia Gardner, Richard C. Berner (University of Washington, Seattle), Kenneth W. Porter (University of Oregon, Eugene), Mrs. ? Crichton (Portland, Oregon), Edwin R. Bingham (University of Oregon, Eugene), Mr. and Mrs. William J. Graeper (Portland, Oregon), Mrs. ? Jenkins (Portland, Oregon), Evelyn Averbuck, Tess Mack, Floyd Ramp (Eugene, Oregon), Vera Ramp, Gertrude Haessler (Eden, New York), Miss ? Gray, Mrs. ? Irwin, Bill Chevalier (Friday Harbor, Washington), Leslie Smith Miller (Gearhart, Oregon), Alma Davidson, Helmi Mattson, and Lela Goodard Fenton.
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1970; 1977; 1987; undated (Box-folder 5/17)
      Correspondents include: Richard C. Berner, Kenneth W. Porter, Arthur Spencer (Oregon Historical Society, Portland), Floyd Ramp (Eugene, Oregon), and Virginia Gardner.
    - Interviews, 1970 April-1973 (Box-folder 5/17)
      Typescript reports and transcriptions include good descriptions and background information on the people Ruuttila interviewed, as well as of their homes when she visited them in person. Some interviews were conducted by telephone.
    - Interviews, 1970 April-June (Box-folder 5/18)
      Subjects: Mrs. Linley Chrichton, Lela Fenton, Elizabeth Oliphant, Marie Louise Feldenheimer, Mrs. Frances Nelson Carroll, Gladys Mackenzie Hug, Alice Bretherton Powell, Theresa Mack, Olive Vinton, and Mrs. Frank Jenkins.
    - Interviews, 1970 July-August (Box-folder 5/19)
      Subjects: Mrs. Lesley Smith Miller, Mrs. Frank Jenkins, Mrs. Frances Nelson Carroll, Claude Washburne, Louise Gray, Mrs. Mortimer Hartwell, and Margaret Beasley Campbell
    - Interviews, 1970 September-December (Box-folder 5/20)
      Subjects: Leila Borchers Irwin, Myra Loveridge Cannon, Erskine Wood, Ruth Trullinger, Alfred Powers, Edward N. Weinbaum, Theresa Mack, and Louis Levy.
    - Interviews, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 5/21)
      Subjects: Lura Cronyn and Lucia Wilkins Moore.
    - With Floyd Ramp, [1970] (Box-folder 5/22)
    - Notes, [1970] (Box-folder 5/23)
    - Research materials collected [photocopies], 1878-1959; undated
      - Profile of Hugh J. Mohan from Pen Portraits, R.R. Parkinson, compiler, 1878 (Box-folder 5/24)
      - Baptismal and genealogical information for John Reed from Trinity Episcopal Church, 1888 (Box-folder 5/24)
      - University of Oregon senior play (cast included Louise Bryant)--yearbook pages and page from scrapbook of Helene Robinson, 1908 (Box-folder 5/24)
      - Charles Jerome Reed's obituaries, 1912 July (Box-folder 5/24)
      - Newspaper notice of marriage of Louise Bryant and John Reed, 1916 July 12 (Box-folder 5/24)
      - Photo and article re. Henry D. Green, The Blue Flame (Northwest Natural Gas newsletter), 1959 January (Box-folder 5/24)
      - Pages from unidentified book in chapter, "'United Front' in the '20's", undated (Box-folder 5/24)
    - Reviews of Friend and Lover, 1982 (Box-folder 5/25)
  - California and Nevada Research, 1970-1971; Sub-series 3
    Evelyn Averbuck served as an interviewer in California for her friend, Virginia Gardner. Margaret Bome served as her interviewer and researcher in Nevada.
    - Interviews by Evelyn Averbuck in California, 1970 June-July (Box-folder 5/26)
      Subjects include: Adele Trullinger, Mrs. Fred Cabanski, Jacob Proebstel, Ben Legere, Sara Bard Field Wood, and Bertha Dorris.
    - Interviews and research by Margaret Bome in Nevada, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5/27)
      Subjects include: Ferris Cunningham and Millie Hunewill Hamblet. Folder includes notes on research in Washoe County and at the Nevada State Historical Society.
- Julia Ruuttila's FBI File, 1941-1993; Series F
  The FBI placed Julia under surveillance beginning in 1941 as a suspected subversive. With Julia's permission, Sandy Polishuk requested Ruuttila's FBI file under the Freedom of Information Act in January 1990. However, the files did not arrive until more than a year after Julia's death. The FBI provided about 500 pages of the total 1,236 pages in Ruuttila's file. Some of the pages are photocopies of her published writings, some are copies of newspaper articles covering her activities, but most are reports and memos. These include annual reports, lists of participants in demonstrations, and narrative reports of organizations and activities. Much detail is blacked out. Some files are from Headquarters (HQ) and some from the Portland District office (PD). They are arranged in that order.
  - FBI responses to Sandy Polishuk's request for the Ruuttila files, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Headquarters files, 1941 February-1972 May (Box-folder 6/2-7)
  - Portland District files, 1941-1977 (Box-folder 6/8-13)
  - Other files with prefix, SE, 1946 October-1956 December (Box-folder 6/14)